<?xml-stylesheet href="transform.xml" type="text/xsl"?>

<kbpage title="Adding and changing this site" backlink="index">

  <section title="The simplest way to submit changes">
    This site is maintained in Subversion. It's designed to be very easy to
    submit changes and new content for. The idea is that this site is a bit like
    a Wiki, but more controlled because it has to go via somebody (me) who can
    filter out the crud. But don't let that stop you scribbing at will!

    The simplest way to do this is just to see a change you want to make, and
    use your favourite text editor to open the URL directly. Emacs can do this
    (via tramp), so can gedit and kate via gnome-vfs and KIO respectively. Or,
    just save the file and open it directly.

    The XML format is simple enough: it's simply HTML with extra bits. Content
    must be in a section tag, and each section must have a title. Lower-case l
    tags simply link the text inside them. Email addresses can be protected by
    reversing them and putting them in email tags. See this page for an
    example. Finally, each kbpage can have a "backlink" which is what you see in
    the top right.

    Once you made your change, send me a unified diff at <email>xc.ivan@ekim</email>.
  </section>

  <section title="A better way">
    So you want to make more changes? Good! The next easiest way is to use this command:
    <type> svn co http://navi.cx/svn/misc/winekb </type>

    And make your changes locally in there. You don't need any special software,
    just a decent web browser (Mozilla/IE6+ will do) and so you can view the
    website locally and any changes you make appear instantly. Then do an "svk
    diff" and send me the results.
  </section>

  <section title="An even better way">
    An even better way is to install <a href="http://svk.elixus.org/">SVK</a> and branch the repository. 

    SVK is a distributed form of Subversion and makes it very easy to
    branch the knowledge base and hack on your local copy, committing
    whenever you like. It's very easy to work with. Firstly install
    it, by using your local Perl/CPAN installation to install module
    "SVK". Or see the website for packages.

    Now initialize SVK on your system: <type> svk depotmap --init </type>
    and then mirror my repository locally like so: <type> svk mirror http://navi.cx/svn/misc/winekb //winekb/remote
$   svk sync //winekb/remote </type>

    Finally create a local branch you can commit to (offline even): <type> svk cp -m 'local branch' //winekb/remote //winekb/local </type>
    And check it out into a working copy: <type> svk co //winekb/remote winekb </type>

    Now you can commit as often as you like. Each patch can be generated with
    "svk -r16" to do revision 16. To see all patches you did, use "svk log".
  </section>
</kbpage>
